Good morning y'all. Today's דף daf is כ"ד, Chaf-Daled, 24, and we
pick up with the two
dots. That's going to be a fun דף daf today. So the
question was רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel said in
the משנה Mishnah that if you see a cow that is nursing
you can assume that it's given birth and then it went on
to say that if you see a cow that's actually nursing a
particular a particular calf then you can assume that that calf is
its child and that it hasn't swapped children to nurse with some
other animals in the barn which means that you can make appropriate
assumptions about which children are the בכור Bechor and which ones are
not not just that a mother has given birth and is exempt
from בכור. Bechor. So the גמרא Gemara is now going to explore
this position. Let's take a look. Second line at the two dots.
איבעיא
להו Iba'ya lehu so they raised the question. דבר בחזקתו דקאמר רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל. Davar be-chezkato de-ka'amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says you retain the חזקה chazakah
your natural assumptions that you would have here that this cow has
given birth and that the child is its child. So what does
that mean? How far do we retain our normal assumptions? Do we
say דאין מרחמת אלא אם כן יולדת de-ein merachemet ela im ken
yoledet that it will not have compassion unless it's given birth which
is an interesting phrase because what it really means here is that
it will not lactate unless it's given birth unless it's given birth
so that if it's lactating it must have given birth. That's the
most basic thing that he said. הא
היכא דאוליד חיי דמרחמי ha heicha de-olid hay de-rachme but if you
know it's given birth maybe we should be concerned that it will
nurse an animal of another calf. או
דילמא o dilma or would you go so far to say דדידה
מרחמא דלא דידה לא מרחמא de-dada rachma ve-lo de-dada lo rachma it
only has compassion on its own it doesn't have compassion on another
so we can also make assumptions about the child not just that
the mother has given birth but also about the child. Now it
would seem that רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel explicitly
addressed that because he says when you see the children you can
assume which one is the mother so we'll see why the גמרא
Gemara thinks that that might be only limited to a particular case.
So the גמרא Gemara says למאי
נפקא מינה lemai nafka mina what's נפקא מינה? nafka mina? למלקי עליה
משום אותו ואת בנו. lemalka alei mishum oto ve-et beno. So when
you see a calf nursing from its mother can we assume that
that's definitely the mother and not just for issues of בכור Bechor
which actually there too there were you know you weren't playing it
safe you were saying some animals definitely are not some animals definitely
are we ignore concerns of חולין בעזרה chullin ba-azarah or concerns of
misuse חולין chullin but here also a consequence for giving somebody lashes.
You see a calf suckling from its mother if you שחט shecht
the mother and the calf you assume you would get lashes for
killing the mother and the child even though the only knowledge that
this is the child is that it was nursing from this calf.
Will we be that certain that this is the mother? אי אמרת
דדידה מרחמא דלא דידה לא מרחמא i amarta de-dada rachma ve-lo de-dada
lo rachma
if we say that it will only have compassion and here again
meaning it will only nurse its own and it won't nurse another
calf
so if that's true לוקי loki you get lashes. ואי אמרת דלא
דידה נמי מרחמא ve-i amarta de-lo de-dada nami rachma
yes it won't give milk until it's given birth but once it's
given birth it will have compassion meaning it will nurse even a
calf that is not its own then לא לוקי lo loki you
would not get lashes. Okay so we know that he clearly says
that if it's nursing that means that it has given birth but
can we also take say definitely means that the animal that it
is nursing is its own child which again seems explicitly addressed so
let's see what's bothering the גמרא. Gemara. So תא שמע ta shema
come in here. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
omer we'll start with the first case in the משנה Mishnah we'll
go from the cases that are easier to dismiss to the ones
that are less easy. הלוקח בהמה מן העובד כוכבים halokeach behema min
ha-oved kochavim if you buy a cow from a non-Jew אינו חושש
שמא בנה של אחרת היה eino choshesh shema binah shel acheret hayah
we are not concerned and it is nursing actually let's add the
keyword right
מניקה meinkah anyway you purchased a nursing animal from a non-Jew you're
not concerned that the reason it's nursing is because of some other
animal's child and not its own. No you assume this had its
own child. So the גמרא Gemara assumes that what the משנה Mishnah
reads it means you just assume this had had its own child.
But the גמרא's Gemara reading it to mean that you assume
the calf that is currently nursing from it is its child. So
the
גמרא Gemara says no מי קתני הוא mi-katani hu
we don't say we're not concerned that this calf is a different
animal's child that's not the point of the משנה. Mishnah. היה קתני
haya katani we're not concerned that it nursed another calf meaning and
it never had given birth. הכי קאמר hachi ka'amar אינו חושש שמא
בנה של אחרת eino choshesh shema binah shel acheret
we're not concerned that the reason it's nursing is because of it
never gave birth and it's some other animal's child. child is the
reason for its nursing. אלא אם כן היה לו ולד מעיקרא. Ella
im ken haya lo vlad me'ikara. The only reason it would be
nursing now is because it had had its own child. So when
the first case in the משנה Mishnah reads if you buy an
animal that is nursing, is nursing the transitive verb, right?
What's the child that's actually suckling? You would say that's also nursing,
right? But you say the mother is nursing, right? A nursing mother.
I guess you can go on both sides of the equation. Anyway,
if you buy a cow, say cow, suppose cow, if you buy
a cow that is nursing, okay, it says we're not concerned that
it was some other child. So what does that mean we're not
concerned it was some other child? So the first way we read
it is means that the calf, we're not concerned is some other
animal's calf and we should assume this is definitely its calf. So
that resolves our question. No, no, no, that's not what it means.
It means we're not concerned that the reason for its nursing is
because some other animal other than it gave birth. We can assume
that it gave birth and that's why it's nursing. So that doesn't
deal with identifying mother child, just to prove that this animal actually
is a mother, it actually gave birth. So let's go to the
next cases which are more explicit. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and
hear.
נכנס בתוך עדרו. Nichnas betoch edro. You go into your barn, literally
flock.
וראה המבכירות מניקות ושאינן מבכירות מניקות. Vera'ah hamavkirot menikot veshe'einan hamavkirot menikot.
You see the ones that have and a lot of animals gave
birth last night and the ones that had never given birth before
are now nursing new young and the ones that had given birth
before are also nursing new young. אינו חושש שמא בנה של זו
בא אצל זו או שמא בנה של זו בא אצל זו. Eino
choshesh shema bnah shel zu ba eitzel zu o shema bnah shel
zo ba eitzel zu. You're not concerned that they switched children and
they're nursing calves that are not their own. And therefore you say
that the ones that are nursing from the ones that have never
given birth before are definitely בכור bechor and the ones that are
nursing from the other ones are definitely not בכור. bechor. So there
you go, it's explicitly our case. An animal's nursing from a cow,
you definitely assume that the animal that is nursing is this animal's
child. Isn't that exactly your question?
You don't want to be particular about it, you can't prove anything
from there. I mean, the גמרא Gemara wants to like, if you
what, you can create doubt in any of these cases. You can
say, oh well, it's not going to leave its own animal.
Ah, thank you very much, Michael. Thank you. Very good, very good,
that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says אמאי,
Amai, if you think that you cannot draw make definite assumptions based
on what animal is nursing, then why do we why do we
assume which is the child? ליחוש, Leichush, why do we not concern
דילמא רחומי רחים, Dilma rachumei racheim,
maybe it is having compassion on another animal's child. So why do
we assume that the animal it's nursing is definitely its own? So
you see we assume that the animal it's nursing is only that
of the mother. Gemara says no, as Michael said, במקום דידה לא
שבקה לדידה ומרחמה אדלא דידה. Bimkom didah lo shavka l'didah u'merachma ad'la
didah.
When its own child is in the same room, it's not going
to leave its own child and nurse the child of another animal.
So therefore if there are multiple children and its child is in
the room, we're going to assume that the only that the one
it's nursing is its own child. But we're talking that we don't
know that its child is in the room. You see a calf
walking by and it's and it's nursing, can we assume that maybe
you know it's babysitting that calf, okay? And maybe its child isn't
around and therefore it's able to nurse another animal. Can we make
that assumption? And if Charlie was here he would tell us what
the likelihood of that is that animals will nurse. But actually that
does happen I believe from what I know that animals that actually
have had young and do nurse their own can sometimes nurse other
animal's children. So the גמרא Gemara said at least if their own
children aren't around, maybe we cannot draw an obvious conclusion that the
nursing calf is its child. So תא שמע, Ta shema, come and
hear. דבר בחזקתו, Davar bechezkato, right, in the ברייתא braita we quoted
yesterday, רבי שמעון בן גמליאל Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel said the matter
retains its חזקה, chazaka, וכן, vechein, that was about when it nurse
it's nursing the cow you say it definitely gave birth and when
it's and when it's nursing particular calves and it's in the barn
you assume the ones it's nursing are its own. וכן היה רבי
שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Vechein haya Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel omer, etc.
So the גמרא's Gemara going to focus on the וכן, vechein, the
way the first case is compared to the second. The difference is
the second case, the one we just left, was when there's a
lot of calves in the barn, a lot of newly newly born
calves, but also its calf is in the barn. So therefore we
couldn't prove anything because there obviously if its own calf is in
the barn it's definitely nursing its own calf. But the first case
was not a lot of cows and a lot of calves. The
first case was just one cow nursing a calf. And it said
oh definitely gave birth and compared it to the second case. So
the גמרא's Gemara now going to focus on the comparison. Let's take
a look. מה לאו, Ma lav, from the fact that those two
cases are being compared, the one with multiple cows and multiple calves
to one cow and one calf, רישא דומיא דסיפא, Reisha dumya deseiifa,
the case the רישא reisha which is one cow and one calf
is like the end which is multiple and multiple. מה סיפא ודאי
דידה, Ma seifa vadai didah, the same way the סיפא seifa it's
definitely nursing its own, that we've already established because its own is
somewhere in the room so therefore we can say it's definitely nursing
its own.
So אף רישא ודאי דידה, Af reisha vadai didah, so even the
first case where it's only one cow and one calf we can
say it's definitely its own and that's the function of the word
וכן, vechein, it connects the two cases. So you see that even
if
we don’t know that its calf is in the room, if it’s
nursing the calf, we assume it’s its own. So the גמרא Gemara
says מי דאיריא, mi de-irya, what's that's a proof? האי כדאית ליה
והאי כדאית ליה, hai kide-it lei ve-hai kide-it lei, each one goes
by a particular context. Even if it says וכן, ve-chein, it doesn't
mean they're the exact same הלכה. halacha. So ומאי וכן? u-mai ve-chein?
So why is it comparing them? אפטורא דבכורה, aptura de-bechora, to say
they're both exempt from the בכורה. bechora. So you have one cow
nursing a calf, you don't know whether it has its own calf
in the room or not, just one cow and one calf, you
obviously assume that this cow has given birth. You can't assume that
the calf maybe is its own, but you can assume it's given
birth and it's פטור patur from בכור. bechor. And similarly, if you
have multiple cows and multiple calves and its calf is definitely in
the room, then you assume the one it's nursing is its own.
And also why are they compared? Because in both cases there's an
exemption for בכור. bechor. But in the second case you can assume
it's its own and in the first case maybe not. So we
still don't know the הלכה, halacha, which is if we know that
its calf is somewhere in the room and it's nursing an animal,
we can assume it's its calf. That's clear. But if we don't
know that and you just see a cow and a calf, a
nursing calf, can you assume for definitely its own or not? That
has not been resolved. Yes.
Is there a reason the גמרא Gemara was really so of
question, in involving questioning this because Rabban Gamliel didn't come out and
explicitly say this is its child?
Otherwise there'd be no question, right? Is that...
Well, no, he did say it's its child. Oh, you mean in
the first case. Yeah, that could be that the first case was
left a little ambiguous. Now, obviously we would have just sort of
said like he's building up, like not only am I going to
tell you that a lactating cow has given birth, I'll even tell
you you can know what the child of the cow is. Right?
So that's what we would have said. But that's why the גמרא
Gemara is saying don't rush to that conclusion. The case when he
tells you you can know the child of the cow is a
case where you know that the child is in the room. And
we want to know would he go so far to say that
when it isn't in the room and that cannot be proved. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara moves on to a different point.
Okay, let's take a look. One of our favorite cases that we
keep on seeing to go back to, you know, when we learned
זבחים, Zevachim, we couldn't get away from פיגול. pigul. So when you're
learning בכורות, Bechoros, you can't get away from the case of נדמה,
nidmeh, the animal that looks like a different animal than the mother.
Okay, so let's take a look. So אמר אמי בר חנא אמר
רבי יוחנן Amar Ami bar Chana Amar Rabbi Yochanan רחזיר שכורך אחר
רחל. rachazir she-koreich achar rachel. You saw a pig that was wrapped
around a nursing sheep, and כורך koreich here means actually wrapped around
and nursing from a nursing sheep, seems to be the case. פטורה
מן הבכורה. petura min ha-bechora. You're exempt. Why? Because, well, if the
sheep is nursing, it definitely gave birth. That's fine. That doesn't matter
whether you think that this pig is its child or not. The
fact that it's nursing means it gave birth. Okay, so that's not
such a חידוש. chiddush. But then we say ואסור באכילה. ve-asur ba-achila.
You can't eat the pig. Now, actually that doesn't because you can't
eat the pig because the question is, is this pig a pig?
That's the question. Or from the fact that it's nursing proves it's
the child of the sheep and it just happens to look like
a pig, but it's not really a pig. That's our question with
always these animals that are not, you know, that the גמרא Gemara
thinks that they are very, you know, whatever. Actually, although Charlie did
show for us, show us that you do have these
crossbreeds of...
very common years ago they had a zebra and some other animal
mating.
Okay, but the גמרא Gemara often, what I think is funny in
the גמרא Gemara is that it often thinks that it could be
like look exactly like a different species. But anyway, so that's the
question. So actually that position seems completely and eminently reasonable. The fact
that the sheep is nursing shows that it's given birth. Who knows
where its child is? And the fact that this looks like a
pig, we're not going to assume it's the offspring of the sheep.
We're going to assume it's a pig and don't eat it. Why
can't we wait to see if
it has split hooves and
chews its cud and then we'd know? It doesn't, no, it has
all the סימנים simanim of a non-kosher animal. But we've seen before
that it's possible from the גמרא's Gemara perspective for a kosher animal
to give birth to an animal that looks exactly like a non-kosher
one.
So therefore ואסור באכילה ve-asur ba-achila because it
might not be its child. All we see is that it's nursing
from it. We don't see know that it's its child. Therefore what?
Therefore we assume it's a random pig that's nursing from the sheep.
Right, so the point is you know what the kosher סימנים simanim
are.
Meaning if it has, if it's a child of a kosher animal,
it might, it has all the סימנים simanim of a pig. It's
split hooves and doesn't chew its cud. It looks like a pig,
it oinks like a pig. The only question is, is it a
pig? If it was born from the sheep, no matter how much
it looks like a pig and how much טריף treif סימנים simanim
it has, it's kosher. It's יוצא מן הטהור. yotzei min ha-tahor. So
the point here is that you cannot assume although it's nursing from
the sheep that it's the child of the sheep. So let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So ואסור באכילה ve-asur ba-achila and it's forbidden in food עד יבוא
ויורה צדק לכם ad yavo ve-yoreh tzedek lachem
until the משיח Mashiach will come and teach you the right law,
which is a very, very interesting way to end it. But it
means like there's some doubt here, but we're only going to be
able to fully resolve the doubt until משיח Mashiach comes. Okay, עד
שיבוא אליהו, ad she-yavo Eliyahu, which is normally the phrase the גמרא
Gemara uses. Anyway, so let's take a look. He was being very
poetic. He was being very poetic, I guess quoting a פסוק pasuk
in הושע. Hoshea. So the גמרא Gemara now analyzes this. פטרנהו מבכורה
כמאן? Paturninu mibechora keman? Exempt from בכורה bechorah why? כרבן שמעון בן
גמליאל, Ke-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel that you assume if it's nursing, it's definitely given birth.
ואסור באכילה? ve-asur ba-achila? It's forbidden in food if you eat because
you don't, you can't assume it is the child of the, of
the sheep. כרבנן? ke-rabbanan? Like the rabbis that you don't assume that
because an animal is nursing that tells you that the calf is
nursing or a pig is nursing, that tells you that that's the
mother, that's the child. So one minute, how can you do that?
How can you one line rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel and the next line rule like the רבנן? rabbanan?
Now I already told you what the obvious resolution is, but hold
on. וסו, ve-su, and more than that, אי רבנן, ee rabbanan, if
we're really following the rabbis' position that you don't make assumptions about
the child and the mother, מאי עד יבוא ויורה צדק לכם? mai
ad yavo ve-yoreh tzedek lachem? What does it mean we have to
wait till משיח Mashiach comes?
עד שיודע לך דבר מיבעי ליה. ad she-yivadeh lecha davar mibaya lei.
Meaning according to the רבנן, rabbanan, right, what's the most you could
say? The most you could say is we don't know. They don't
say for sure it's not the mother, we say, they say we
don't know that if a calf is nursing whether, whether it is
the child of the, of the sheep. So that, what would be
the doubt? So the רבנן rabbanan would say don't eat it, it
might not be the child of this sheep. So then you say,
oh, until משיח Mashiach comes, so what's משיח Mashiach going to do?
He's going to tell us whether it was the child of the
sheep or not. Fine, but there's a problem because telling somebody facts,
determining facts, although it's an important part of the הלכה halacha process,
not that you don't need משיח Mashiach for it, it's an important
part of the halachic
process usually at least as important as knowing what the הלכה halacha
is,
but nevertheless you wouldn't call that הוראה. hora’ah. הוראה, hora’ah, which means
giving halachic ruling, meaning making a decision about הלכה. halacha. Okay, so
we would not have said עד יבוא ויורה צדק לכם, ad yavo
ve-yoreh tzedek lachem, give הוראה, hora’ah, if all we needed to do
was to determine the facts of whether this pig was the offspring
of the sheep. What should we have said? We should have said
not עד יבוא ויורה, ad yavo ve-yoreh, עד שיודע לך דבר מיבעי
ליה ad she-yivadeh lecha davar mibaya lei until you can figure out
the facts. Okay, so we don't understand it, meaning why we assume
that like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that the
sheep has given birth. Then we're not assuming that this pig is
the child of the sheep. Well, that's normally the רבנן's rabbanan position,
not רבן שמעון בן גמליאל's, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel so make up
your mind who you're ruling like. And number two, if you want
to emphasize there's a doubt here, according to the רבנן, rabbanan, the
only doubt is what's the story with this pig, what's its nature,
you know, is it the child of the sheep or not? So
they should have used a different phrase to express that
we are worried, you know, חשש. chashash.
So it's all רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. So
that, so very good, so that's what the גמרא Gemara is working
up to. So that's not the good way of reading this, that
it's a split between רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
and the רבנן rabbanan which doesn't make any sense. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: וכי תימא, ve-chi teima, maybe you'll say here's
a much better read of this, which is what, you know, I
said when I, when I read it to you.
מספקא ליה אי אליבא דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל אי כרבנן. mesafka lei
ee aliba de-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel ee ke-rabbanan. It's saying we don't
know, so we play it safe. פטור patur from בכורה bechorah like
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, but don't eat the
pig like the רבנן, rabbanan, we'll play it safe. So that's why,
that's how we're splitting the vote because we're really just playing it
safe. One minute. אי מספקא ליה, ee mesafka lei, if you have
a doubt, אמאי פטור מן הבכורה? amai patur min ha-bechorah? Then why
is the mother exempt? If you're playing it safe, then you should
say ספק בכורה safek bechorah afterwards, right? וסו, ve-su, and in addition,
מי מספקא ליה? mi mesafka lei? Since when did we have a
doubt how we rule about this? If you remember the whole end
of yesterday's דף daf was how we definitely rule like רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel and we're going to say that
again here. ואמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, ve-amar Rabbah
bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, the same רבה בר בר חנה
Rabbah bar bar Chana says in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, כל מקום ששנה רבן שמעון בן גמליאל במשנתנו הלכה כמותו, kol
makom she-shanah Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel be-mishnateinu halacha kemoto, whenever רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel voices an opinion in our משנה,
mishnah, this is interesting, not only in our משנה mishnah where it's
uncontested, even if he voices an opinion that's debated in the משנה,
mishnah, whenever he voices an opinion, הלכה כמותו, halacha kemoto, we rule
like him, חוץ מערב וצידן וראיה אחרונה chutz me-arev ve-tzidan ve-raya achrona
except for these three cases of ערב, arev, צידן, tzidan, and ראיה
אחרונה. raya achrona. And since רש״י Rashi doesn't tell us what they
are, I mean I know what they are, but since I'm not
going to bother unpacking that right now, okay, that's not exactly our
topic, there are three times where, where we don't rule, but here
we rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, so
there's no doubt. So we have to be able to explain this
whole statement about the pig nursing from the sheep within the position
of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. So let's take
a look. לעולם פשיטא ליה כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל. le-olam peshita lei
ke-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. You're right. He holds like רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. So why is the mother that's nursing,
the sheep nursing the pig, the mother's exempt, she definitely has given
birth? She's definitely given birth, therefore the next animal is definitely not
a בכור. bechor. Now this pig, what's its story? Can we, why
don't we say it's מותר באכילה, mutar be-achila, this is definitely its
child and it's something that's born from a kosher animal, it looks
totally like a pig and so we permit it? So let's take
a look. מיהו מספקא ליה, mihu_mesafka_lei, here's our question, he doesn't know,
אי סבר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל יולדת מרחמת או אינה מרחמת? ee
savar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel yoledet merachemet o einah merachemet? The question
we raised at the beginning of the דף. daf. If does רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel go so far to say
that the animal nursing, the calf nursing, is definitely the child of
this cow or this sheep. Okay, does he say that? If we
know, if they're definitely, the child is in the room and there's
an animal nursing, we know it's definitely the child of the cow.
But if you just have two animals, a mother and a child,
and they're nursing, can we say it's definitely mother-child relationship? So we
don't know. If we could say definitely, the pig would be the
child of the sheep, it would be a נדמה, nidmeh, a weird-looking
child, and it would be מותר באכילה. mutar b'achila. If we have
a doubt, we're not going to eat the pig. Maybe the pig
came from, you know, is a pig and just happens to be
nursing from the sheep. Okay, and therefore it all works within רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. אי הכי, ee hachi,
and therefore it says, and therefore by the way the פסוק pasuk
makes sense, עד שיבוא ויורה צדק לכם, ad sheyavo v'yoreh tzedek lachem,
because now it's not a question of fact, it's a question of
הלכה, halacha, meaning, yes, the הלכה halacha is to determine fact, but
it's still a question of הלכה. halacha. Right? If I knew what
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel held, I would say
that either this sheep is ודאי vadai a sheep, either this pig
is ודאי vadai a pig, or I would say this pig is
ודאי vadai a sheep. But right now I don't know what he
would say about determining the mother-child relationship, and therefore I have to
say play it safe and treat this pig like a normal pig.
Let's just read a little more and then there's a question, the
גמרא Gemara says one minute. אי הכי, ee hachi, if that's the
point, אדאשמעינן חזיר, adashmi'inan chazir, why tell us the case of this
בשר basar case of a pig? לשמעינן טלה, lishmi'inan taleh,
tell us the case of a sheep nursing from a sheep, and
about the question about you can't give lashes for אותו ואת בנו,
oto v'et bno, because of, you know, it would be a bigger
חידוש chiddush to say that if it's a sheep nursing from a
sheep, then I still can't say it certainly is the mother. To
say a pig nursing from the sheep might not be the mother
is not such a חידוש. chiddush. But a sheep nursing from a
sheep and say I still don't know for sure, that would have
been a bigger חידוש. chiddush. So let's take a look.
הגמרא haGemara says חזיר איצטריכא ליה. chazir itztricha lei. No, we wanted
to tell you the case of the pig. דאי אשמעינן טלה, de'ee
ashmi'inan taleh, had you told me the case of the sheep nursing
from the
sheep, הוי אמינא, hava amina, אי תמצא
לומר דסבר יולדת מרחמא דמינא,
ee timtza lomar desavar yoledet merachama
demina, דמינא, demina, yeah, yeah, דלאו מינה לא. delav mina lo. Even
if he held that a sheep would nurse an animal that is
not its own, that would only be if it was still of
its own species. You can certainly metaphorize this entire גמרא Gemara about
how people, you know, about do you care about other people's children?
Do you care about people that aren't like you? You know, so
that's basically the question here. And first we know, what?
If your own kid is in the room, you only care about
your kid. Hey, what if your kid isn't in the room? Will
you care about other people's children? Will you care about them if
they're not of your same ethnic background or whatever, socioeconomic class? So,
the fact is we thought that the חידוש chiddush would be that
if it's nursing a sheep, then you really would think that this
sheep is the mother-child, and no, it's still a doubt. But says
you could go the other way. You could say maybe it's prepared
to nurse other
baby sheep because at least it's like it, but it won't nurse
a pig. And if it's nursing a pig, the only reason it
would nurse a pig is if the pig is its own child.
Okay? So, דלאו מינה לא, delav mina lo, it would never nurse
an animal that is not a sheep. And therefore if it is
nursing a pig, it must be that the pig is really its
own child. So אשמעינן, ashmi'inan, what do they say? A child only
a mother could love.
So this pig is a child only a mother could love and
therefore it has to be its mother. So אשמעינן חזיר, ashmi'inan chazir,
so therefore it had to tell us the case of the pig.
דאפילו דלאו מינה נמי, de'afilu delav mina nami, even if it's nursing
something that is not its species, on the one hand you'd say
it's definitely not its mother, but on the other hand you could
say why else would it nurse a pig unless it really is
its
child? איכא למימר דילמא מרחמא, ika l'meimar dilma merachama, maybe in this
case the only reason it would nurse a pig is because it's
its child? No, even here we can't know for sure. So it's
a way of telling us also, it's a fun case, believe me,
a week from now you're not going to forget about the pig
nursing from the sheep, okay? So anyway, so therefore we rule like
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, it definitely has given
birth if it's nursing, if its child is in the room and
it's nursing then it's definitely nursing its child, but if it's just
nursing an animal, you can't know for sure whether that's its child
or not, whether that animal, we don't know for sure what רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel would say. Would he go
so far to say it definitely is or definitely not? We don't
know, regardless of whether that thing that it's nursing is its own
type, it's a sheep, or whether it's a pig. והיינו דאמר רבי
יוחנן, v'hainu d'amar Rabbi Yochanan, and that's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says, אחאי ברבי, Achai b'Rabbi, so this אחאי ברבי, Achai b'Rabbi, ברבי
b'Rabbi is like an honorific, this great person אחאי Achai asked the
question, ראה חזיר שכרוך אחר רחל, ra'ah chazir shekaruch achar rachel, again
you see this pig that is wrapped around a mother sheep and
presumably nursing from it, מהו, mahu, what's the question? So מאי קמיבעיא
ליה, mai kamiba'ya lei, what exactly is the framing of that question?
What are you getting at? Here's the question: אילימא לבכורה קמיבעיא ליה,
eileima l'bechora kamiba'ya lei, maybe his questioning whether the mother is חייב
chayav in בכור, bechor, קמיבעיא ליה אי הלכה כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל.
kamiba'ya lei ee halacha k'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. So that's the question.
He just wants to know, can we assume the mother has given
birth? Is the mother exempt from בכורה? bechorah? Do we rule like
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel or do we rule
like the Rabbis that a lactating mother is exempt from בכורה? bechorah?
So if that's true, why give a crazy case with a pig?
Then תיבעי ליה tibaie lei give a simple case that a sheep
is nursing another sheep and we want to know, can we assume
that it's given birth or not? So the Gemara says fine, it's
not that, that's not what he's asking. כי קמיבעיא ליה, ki kamibaia
lei, here's the question: either לבכורה ואליבא דרבנן, libechorah v'aliba d'Rabbanan,
what is the law for בכורה bechorah according to the Rabbis? The
Rabbis who normally assume that a lactating animal you cannot know for
sure it's given birth, what would you say in the case of
the pig? And we'll see why that might be different. Or לאכילה
ואליבא דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל, l'achilah v'aliba d'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, can
you eat this pig according to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel, like the question raised before, can you assume it's the
offspring of the sheep? So now we're going to spell that out.
לבכורה ואפילו לרבנן, libechorah v'afilu l'Rabbanan, so to בכורה bechorah even
according to the
Rabbis. דאמרי מרחמא, d'amri merachama, the Rabbis say normally if a sheep
is, an animal's lactating, maybe it didn't give birth, maybe it's having
compassion
on another animal—again, interesting that it frames the idea that it can
lactate because of its compassion, but as we pointed out yesterday, you
know, hormones actually lead to lactation, sometimes, again, there's been apparently documented
cases where people adopt infants and mothers begin to lactate—so maybe it's
having compassion. So the Rabbis say it's possible it could lactate without
giving birth. That's what they normally say, and therefore it's a ספק
safek whether whether this is exempt from בכורה. bechorah. So one minute,
כי מרחמא ki merachama maybe they don't, maybe they limit that. Maybe
they say, when will it lactate, right, for another animal? דמינה, demina,
again, like we said before, if it's another one of its own
kind. דלאו מינה לא, delav mina lo,
it won't lactate for an animal, it won't start to lactate for
an animal that's not its own kind. So you're saying just because
it sees נעבעך, nebech, this homeless pig, it's not going to start
to lactate. So if it is nursing a pig, obviously it did
not begin to produce milk because of the pig, so it must
have begun to produce milk because of its own child and therefore
maybe we can say it's ודאי vadai is exempt from בכורה. bechorah.
Of course it's a little funny. No, so that's the question. In
the case of the pig, would they say it's still a ספק
safek or would they say it's ודאי vadai exempt from בכורה bechorah
because it certainly wasn't producing milk for the pig?
Right, so that's what, so that's
the question.
Or, I'll give you another thing which actually is more, maybe it
started producing its milk for another sheep even though right now it's
nursing the pig. But nevertheless, it hasn't given birth to its own.
Just because it's not nursing for, just because it didn't produce milk
for this pig doesn't mean that it produced milk for its own.
But again, as I'm saying, this seems to be very far-fetched to
say that it has now, it never gave birth and is now
nursing this pig.
Okay, fine, got it. So that's why the גמרא Gemara thinks that
it raises the question. So therefore there's a good reason to think
that in this case the Rabbis would say it ודאי vadai is
פטור pattur from בכורה, bechorah, it definitely had its own child. Okay,
fine. או דילמא, o dilma, because the גמרא Gemara is not so
certain as you are, או דילמא דלאו מינה נמי מרחמא, o dilma
delav mina nami merachama, maybe even if it's not its own kind
it has רחמנות rachmanut and it can produce milk. So that's the
question according to the רבנן. Rabbanan. Will there be a case where
they say it definitely has had a child? Now, לאכילה ואפילו רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל. l'achilah v'afilu Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Now we want
to know, can you eat the pig according to רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel who normally says you can make assumptions
that it's given birth and that its child מותר. muttar. אם תמצא
לומר סברא יולדת מרחמא, im timtza lomar savra yoledet merachama,
even if he says that after an animal has given birth it
will have compassion
on another animal—so if it's nursing an animal you cannot assume mother-child
relationship—maybe דמינה, demina, maybe that's only if it's its own species. דלאו
מינה, delav mina, if it's not its own species it would never
nurse an animal that wasn't its own species and therefore לא, lo,
and therefore if it's nursing this pig, the only reason it's nursing
this pig is because it's its child, so therefore you could eat
the pig. או דילמא, o dilma, or would we say דלאו מינה
נמי מרחמא delav mina nami merachama that it would also nurse from
another species and therefore you cannot assume that this pig is a
child and as soon as you can't assume it's its child you
won't be able to eat it. So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו,
teiku, it's left unresolved, which is a good thing because I think
it would be hard unless you actually saw with your own eyes
a sheep giving birth to a pig.
Even so, it's probably pretty rare that a sheep nurses its pig.
I much feel much more much more confident saying that if it's
nursing a pig I'm going to assume it's a pig and not
eat it. So anyway, but now the גמרא Gemara is left with
that question, which is רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
assumes if it's lactating it gave birth—very reasonable assumption—definitely gave birth, definitely
פטור pattur from בכורה. bechorah. If its kid is in the room
and it's nursing the child then we assume that it's its own
child for הלכות halakhot of בכורה bechorah and also אסור והיתר. issur
v'hetter. But the one question we don't know is given that it's
given birth and given that it's currently nursing a particular calf or
child can we say definitely that this is its child? And that
we say is not so clear. That actually we do know that
nursing animals will sometimes nurse those that are not their young. So
the גמרא Gemara leaves it as a doubt and
since...
one of these like ממה *mimma* cases but you know in other
words a kosher animal gave birth to a pig-like looking animal doesn't
have to have all the סימני טהרה *simanei tahara* to be טהור
*tahor* so even if
it doesn't have it looks exactly like a pig it chews its
cud and all those things and it doesn't chew its cud excuse
me and all
those things right but didn't we say you can still eat it
but let's say the other way around like looks like it does
have the it looks basically pig-like but it does have the split
hooves and it's chewing its cud and it's nursing from its mother
then can we say we can eat it?
What?
What do you mean an animal that just walked off the street
and we have no idea what where it came from?
No we see this pig nursing from its mother but it's not
exactly like a pig because it does have split hooves and we
see it also chews its cud now it's nursing from its mother.
You're just asking a סתם *stam* question what happens if an animal
from a non-kosher species but in a particular animal does not have
the non-kosher does not have the
does
not have the סימן *siman*? No even more than that I'm saying
like this pig is nursing from a pig it happens to chew
its cud and has split hooves maybe it's not even a pig
but you know do we say do we say that if it's
actually nursing from a kosher animal and it has all the סימני
טהרה *simanei tahara* that it is kosher because it is its son?
I mean that that you know I don't
know I don't know so you're asking a question what other indications
might we have to allow us to assume that this is definitely
its child if it didn't and let's say it looks like a
pig and has some wool on it right at what point would
we have enough of an indication that we can assume it's its
child but I don't think it's based on if anything I would
certainly not say it's based on whether it's still exhibiting kosher and
non-kosher סימנים *simanim* I would say whether it has מקצת סימנים *miktzat
simanim* of the אם *em* which is an issue is the most
relevant question which is an issue the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* raised before
as well
so even if it has all kosher סימנים *simanim*
and nursing then I would not think necessarily that means that no
that we could assume that it's its child not necessarily okay let's
take a look at the next משנה mishnah. *Mishnah* רבי יוסי בן
המשולם Rabbi Yossi ben Hamishulam. *Rabbi Yosei ben HaMeshullam* אומר *omer* רבי
יוסי בן המשולם Rabbi Yossi ben Hamishulam. *Rabbi Yosei ben HaMeshullam* says
השוחט את הבכור hashochet es habechor, עושה מקום בקופיץ מכאן ומכאן mikan
umikan, *hashocheit et habechor oseh makom bekupitz mikan umikan* so you're going
to שחט shechted *shacht* a בכור bechor *bechor* now there's a problem
which is you're not allowed to shear a שור *shor* לא תגוז
lo sagoz, בכור bechor. שורך *lo tagoz bechor shorecha* you're not allowed
to really shear all קדשים *kodashim* so תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot* wants to
know why are we not talking why don't we say something like
this by other קדשים *kodashim* but the simplest answer is because the
פסוק *pasuk* is explicit by בכור bechor. *bechor* okay לא תגוז בכור
bechor. שורך *lo tagoz bechor shorecha* so you're not allowed to shear
your בכור bechor. *bechor* sheep so what are you going to do
you're going to שחט shecht *shacht* it why are you going to
שחט shecht *shacht* it not as a קרבן *korban* you're going to
שחט shechting *shacht* it because it has a מום mum. *mum* okay
so you're going to שחט shecht *shacht* it and eat it you're
a כהן *kohen* the only thing is that trying to שחט shecht?
*shacht* through wool is not a very easy thing to do and
you might slip and you might whatever ruin the שחיטה shechitah, *shechitah*
so therefore you want to clear off a space by the neck
remove the wool from it so you can שחט *shacht* is the
removing of the wool from the neck area going to be the
איסור issur דאורייתא *issur d'Oraita* of shearing your sheep okay well here's
what you do so השוחט את הבכור עושה מקום בקופיץ *hashocheit et
habechor oseh makom bekupitz* you make a space literally this sounds like
you use a קופיץ *kupitz* which is like a cleaver to make
a space to sort of cut away at the at the hair
to make a space but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually says because
it's bothered about why will this not be the prohibition of לא
תגוז *lo tagoz* which is certainly the concern of the משנה mishnah.
*Mishnah* and the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* reads it as you pluck with
your hands the hair out of the neck or you remove the
hair away with your hands in order to make space for the
קופיץ *kupitz* now meaning the קופיץ *kupitz* is what you're going to
שחט *shacht* with I know that's how it read it it read
it like מקום לקופיץ *makom lakupitz* for the sake of the קופיץ
*kupitz* the problem is as תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says when did you
when do we ever find that you use a קופיץ *kupitz* like
a cleaver for שחיטה shechita. *shechitah* now certainly you're not going to
do like that which is normally what you do with a קופיץ
*kupitz* you could go like that you could use it like a
שחיטה shechita *shechitah* knife but it's very bizarre that that actually is
what we you know is is the scenario be that as it
may תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says the נפקא מינה nafka mina *nafka mina*
is is that if you want to use a קופיץ *kupitz* for
your שחיטה shechita... *shechitah* it's obviously a bigger כלי kli, *kli* than
a שחיטה *shechitah* knife so you have to make more space so
it's saying you can sort of clear away enough space for the
קופיץ *kupitz* that's the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* reads it what
is clearing space you mean like removing hair removing hair right but
just pushing
it well the point is clearly the hair is going to be
removed the question the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is going to get to
is whether it was intentional or not
why should you need to remove the hair
in the first place I don't know apparently it will well רש"י
*Rashi* says that if the knife gets between the hair and the
skin it could be חלדה *chaladah* which was one opinion about חלדה
*chaladah* in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* classic חלדה *chaladah* is when the
knife is between the sort of goes between the סימנים *simanim* but
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wanted to say if it was buried in
the hair maybe that's a פסול *psul* by itself but it seems
like regardless תוספות *Tosafot* doesn't like that it seems regardless it'll just
you know it'll you know it'll like
it'll make you slip right it'll prevent you from doing it properly
right you won't be able to make a clean cut it'll get
caught in the hair and it'll like you know and so that
seems to be the concern what the wool's
very oily the wool is oily all right
either way you know you want to if you want to cut
the skin in one quick clean cut right without any hesitation and
without any whatever you don't want there to be hair in the
way so you remove the hair but the question the reason I'm
being ambiguous in translating this משנה mishnah *Mishnah* is because the גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara* raises the question whether are you intentionally pulling the hair
out the first thing the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says is we we
have to assume you're not using a כלי *kli*. If you're using
a כלי, it makes it too much like גיזה, gizzah, too much
like shear. So you have to assume you're using your hand. And
then within that, the גמרא Gemara and therefore בקיפיץ bikupitz really means
for the sake of the קיפיץ. kupitz. Then within that, the גמרא
Gemara is going to say, can you intentionally pull out the hair,
and it's still not defined as shearing, or are you only really
trying to move the hair out of the way, and then if
some hair comes out, then okay, it came out, it was unintended,
it was... and that's going to be the גמרא's Gemara question.
What happens to the hair on the leather after it's killed? What?
Then you can... that's an interesting question. I assume... can what... can
you use the wool after you've שחט'ed it? Is there איסור גיזה
issur gizzah after מיתה? misah?
I assume not. What about on יום טוב? Yom Tov? Yeah, I
assume that's all מותר בהנאה. mutar behana'ah. I mean, the גמרא Gemara
does say אין לך בה אלא היתר אכילה, ein lach bah ela
heter achilah, but the real איסור is גיזה ועבודה. gizzah va'avodah. You
know, I'll get back to you on that. That's a very good
point. I'd be surprised if it's not in the גמרא, Gemara I
just don't remember off the top of my head, so I'll get
back to you. Let's finish the משנה. mishnah Wait a minute, let's
finish the משנה. Mishna? Okay. השוחט את הבכור, so okay, עושה מקום
בקיפיץ. oseh makom bikupitz. You make a space, again, for the קיפיץ,
kupitz, for the cleaver, מכאן ומכאן,
this and that way, you pull the hair both sides, והתולש את
השער. vehatolesh es hasaar.
So again, the simple reading here is you can intentionally pull out
the hair, but it might mean and it would be okay if
the hair got pulled out if you want to read it as
non-intentional. But the simple read is definitely you can intentionally pull the
hair out to make way, ובלבד שלא יזיזנו ממקומו, uvelvad shelo yezizenu
mimkomo, but don't remove it. Leave the pulled out wool sort of
intertwined with the other wool. Why? Because if you pull it out
completely, it looks too much like גיזה. gizzah. And once you see
somebody pulling out wool and keeping the wool, you're going to think
that you can do גיזה gizzah and so on. So therefore, keep
it embedded within the rest of the wool. Okay. וכן תולש את
השער לראות מקום מום. vechen tolesh es hasaar liros makom mum.
Another case where this would be permissible is let's say there's a
blemish and you have to determine is it a blemish or not.
You've got to get a good look at the blemish, but the
wool is in the way. So you can pull out the hair
in order to look at the blemish. Now clearly, the simple read
of this משנה Mishna, is intentional. You can intentionally pull out the
hair if you need to for שחיטה, and you can intentionally pull
out if you need to for the מום. But that's the question
the גמרא is going to raise: can it really be done intentionally,
or is this only if it happened incidentally? Yes.
Yeah, and this is what I was trying to understand. I mean,
honestly, what's the big deal? I mean, especially if you're using a
קיפיץ, kupitz, which is not like your usual shearing implement, and then
you're only doing it around the neck, it's only a little bit.
First of all, why would it even be a problem with גיזה?
gizzah? I mean, to me it seems גיזה gizzah is like, you
know, when you're like shearing it to use and all that, and
here...
So let's see what the גמרא says. Okay, so let's look at
the גמרא. אמר רב הלכה כרבי יוסי בן המשולם. amar Rav halachah
k'Rabbi Yossi ben Hamishulam. So the first point is we rule like
רבי יוסי בן המשולם. Rebbe Yose ben HaMeshulam, If you remember yesterday,
that was the whole question, that רב Rav made these statements where
you go like all the non-debated משניות, mishnayos, and he also made
a particular statement that we rule like רבי יוסי בן המשולם. Rebbe
Yose ben HaMeshulam So here we're quoting that in context. בעו מיניה
מרב הונא. ba'u minei meiRav Huna. They asked רב הונא Rav Huna
the following question: כנגדו ביום טוב מהו? kenegdo b'Yom Tov mahu?
You're allowed to שחט on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Let's say on
יום טוב Yom Tov you want to שחט your sheep. You want
to have some lamb chops for יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay, can
you similarly pull out the hair? Because now it's not a question
about לא תגוז, גיזה, gizzah, it's a problem about one of the
ל"ט מלאכות, lamed tes melachos, מלאכה melachah of shearing, but it's... can
you do it also for the sake of שחט'ing on יום טוב?
Yom Tov? Okay, so מהו, mahu, what's the story? טעמא דרבי יוסי
בן המשולם משום דקסבר תולש
לאו היינו גוזז. ta'ama d'Rabbi Yossi ben Hamishulam mishum d'kasavar tolesh lav
haynu gozez. Maybe it's because when you're תולש, tolesh, and this is
why it's important for the גמרא to say you're using your hand,
what's the difference between pulling out hair and shearing hair? Well, certainly
the most obvious difference is are you using a vessel or are
you using your hand? Now you could have said, again going back
to the possibility of reading the משנה Mishna בקיפיץ bikupitz with a
כלי, that any vessel that's not the normal shearing vessel still is
not considered גוזז. gozez. But the גמרא doesn't want to go there.
The גמרא wants to limit it to תולש. tolesh. Maybe כלאחר יד,
k'le'achar yad, but fundamentally, in definitionally, if it's using a vessel, it's
גוזז. gozez. It might not be a normal vessel to use, but
it's גוזז. gozez. But if you're using your hand, it's a different
act. It's pulling, it's not shearing. Okay,
so therefore the question is, is that what's going on here? And
if that's what it is, that the reason it's permissible since it's
תולש, tolesh, it's a totally different act than גוזז, gozez, well by
יום טוב, Yom Tov, the תורה Torah never says don't do גיזה
gizzah on יום טוב. Yom Tov. What does the תורה Torah say
on יום טוב? Yom Tov? וביום טוב... u'v'Yom Tov... wait a minute...
וביום טוב אסור דהוה ליה עוקר דבר מגידולו. u'v'Yom Tov assur d'hava
lei oker davar migidulo.
But by יום טוב Yom Tov it's different. By יום טוב Yom
Tov you're pulling something up from where it grows. Now that is
a bizarre phrase, because normally עוקר דבר מגידולו oker davar migidulo when
it's coming in a שבת Shabbos יום טוב Yom Tov category is
coming to prohibit what? Can anybody like... what?
Reaping, pulling an apple off of a tree, right, pulling things, growing
things from the land. Now there is a מלאכה melachah of גוזז,
gozez, but it's not framed that way. Nobody says גוזז gozez is...
not nobody, there is an opinion, but anyway, normally it's not said
that גוזז gozez is a form of קוצר, kotzer, that shearing your
sheep is like pulling an apple from a tree. So גוזז gozez
is its own category. But what the גמרא means by this is
that it's not defined by... narrow definition of גוזז. gozez. By שבת
Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov we have a concept of an
אב av and a תולדה. toldah. We have a concept of anything
that is in the same abstract category. So even if it's technically
not the act of גוזז, gozez, it still is doing the same
thing, it's still removing hair from the sheep. So from a יום
טוב Yom Tov perspective, that should be אסור. assur. It doesn't have
to be, I'll give you an example. Let's say you say one
of the מלאכות melachos of שבת Shabbos is baking. Well, you know
what, it's equally אסור, assur, cooking and frying and all those things.
So even though nobody says that's baking, it doesn't have to be
the exactly narrowly defined act, it has to be in the same
category. So therefore, it says what's going on in this משנה? Mishna
Is it that it's not narrowly defined as גוזז? gozez? Then that's
only a בכור bechor point. But for יום טוב, Yom Tov, it
doesn't matter, it's a broader category and it would include removing hair
even if it's through your hand. That's one way, even though
it's for שחיטה.
Still doing the מלאכה. melacha. That's one way of understanding it.
Aren't these two different אבות מלאכות? avos melachos?
What? גוזז gozez is not a מלאכה. melacha. גוזז gozez is, I
mean it is a מלאכה, melacha, but in the context of our
משנה, Mishna. it's a prohibition by בכור. לא תגז בכור שורך. lo
tagoz bechor shorecha. So that's for בכור.
Yes, he's conflating it to,
I know, the phrase עוקר דבר מגידולו oke’a davar migidulo is very
strange. For now, we'll just assume the way most אחרונים acharonim assume
it means is it's a way of saying it's a more larger
abstract category which doesn't have to be narrow גוזז, gozez, which includes
other ways of removing hair.
He's not conflating it to קוצר, kotzer, right?
No, he's not conflating it with קוצר. kotzer. Okay, he just borrowed
the phrase, but he didn't really mean it. Okay, so therefore, או
דילמא, od dilma, where do we say בעלמא סבר רבי יוסי בן
המשולם תולש היינו גוזז? ba'alma savar Rebbe Yose ben HaMeshulam tolesh hayinu
gozez? The reason of the משנה Mishna has nothing to do with
it's not defined as גוזז. gozez. Let it be defined as גוזז,
gozez, and we're still going to מתיר matir it. How can you
מתיר matir it? It's גוזז gozez of a בכור. והיינו טעמא דשרי,
vehayinu ta'ama d'shari,
here's why he's מתיר matir it, דהוה ליה דבר שאינו מתכוין, d'hava
lei davar she'eino miskaven,
because he's going to read the משנה Mishna? that you did it
unintentionally. You were just trying to clear away the space and it
was unintentional. וביום טוב דבר שאינו מתכוין מותר. ubiyom tov davar she'eino
miskaven mutar.
And by יום טוב Yom Tov that would also be permissible. So
here's a very good question. Basically, תוספות, what this huge תוספות is
about is, why do you have to go to יום טוב? Yom
Tov? Just frame the question in the משנה. Mishna Is the משנה
Mishna allowing me to do this intentionally or even not intentionally? Only
not intentionally or even intentionally? Okay, and I'll tell you תוספות's answer
to that in a minute. But the way we're framing that is,
what's the reason of the משנה? Mishna If it is the reason
of the משנה Mishna that using your hands is not גוזז, gozez,
and therefore you could even do it intentionally. Or is the reason
of the משנה Mishna that yes, using your hands is גוזז, gozez,
and it's not because it's not גוזז, gozez, but the reason, and
therefore the משנה Mishna is only allowing it when it's unintentional. You're
not trying to remove the hair if it happens unintentionally. And one
of the נפקא מינות nafka minas is, is the משנה Mishna only
when you're doing it unintentionally? And the other נפקא מינה is, what
would be the story by יום טוב? Yom Tov? Okay, so let's
take a look at what the גמרא says.
So what about the שוחט shochet then? The שוחט shochet sounds like
you're doing it for שחיטה intentionally.
Not doing it for שחיטה... No, you're not pulling the hair, you're
clearing space. But you're just trying to move the hair aside, and
if it happens to be pulled out... Now again, the simple sense
of the משנה Mishna. is unquestionably that you're doing it intentionally. Okay,
but anyway, let's take a look at what the גמרא says. So
אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to them, זיל ושיילו לרב חננאל.
zil ush’alu l’Rav Chananel. Go ask רב חננאל, Rav Chananel, אי אמר
לכו כרבי יוסי בן המשולם, i amar lach k’Rebbe Yose ben HaMeshulam,
and if he tells you we rule like רבי יוסי בן המשולם,
Rebbe Yose ben HaMeshulam. if you say to them, רב חננאל, Rav
Chananel, what's the story, can we pull out hair for if we
want to שחט a sheep on יום טוב? Yom Tov? And he
says, oh, well we rule like רבי יוסי בן המשולם here by
בכור. So if he uses the בכור case to answer your
יום טוב Yom Tov question, then איפשט לכו כל הלכה, ifshat lach
kol halacha, because meaning then you can figure out what the הלכה
halacha is, right? Because that was our whole question. Can you apply
this משנה Mishna to יום טוב? Yom Tov? So ask him if
he uses this משנה Mishna to give you a פסק, psak, you'll
know your answer. So אתו שיילו, asu she'alu, they went and they
asked רב חננאל, Rav Chananel, what's the story, can you pull out
the wool to שחט? אמר להו, amar lehu, הכי אמר רב, hachi
amar Rav, I'll tell you what the story is on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. הלכה כרבי יוסי בן המשולם, halacha k'Rebbe Yose ben HaMeshulam,
we rule like רבי יוסי בן המשולם. So אתו לקמיה
דרב הונא, asu l'kamei d’Rav Huna,
they went to רב הונא Rav Huna and they said, we asked
him this יום טוב Yom Tov question, he quoted us this משנה.
Mishna So he says, okay fine. אמר להו, amar lehu, כנגדו ביום
טוב מותר. k'negdo biyom tov mutar. So if he's quoting this משנה
Mishna where it says it's מותר mutar and you asked a יום
טוב Yom Tov question, so he's telling you that it's מותר mutar
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So you really wonder why what he
added, it was clear that he was telling you it was מותר,
mutar, but the point is that there is the answer to your
question. Your question is, can we apply it? And the answer is
yes. Now why can you apply it? So we are taking for
granted that by יום טוב Yom Tov using your hand would still
be a מלאכה. melacha. So therefore, if you can apply this משנה
Mishna to יום טוב, Yom Tov, what it's telling you is, the
reason of this משנה Mishna is not because you used your hand,
because using your hand would have been just as much of a
problem on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So it would have been, meaning
using your hand definitely would have been a problem on יום טוב
Yom Tov and therefore if that was the reason of the משנה
it would not have been relevant to יום טוב. Yom Tov. So
therefore the reason of the משנה must have been that it happened
without intention, דבר שאינו מתכוין
מותר, davar she'eino miskaven mutar, and something that happens without intention is
okay, and if that's the reason of the משנה you can apply
it also to a case by יום טוב, Yom Tov, even though
we're dealing with a definite מלאכה. melacha. איתמר נמי *itmar nami* also
אמר רב חנניה בן שמיה משמיה דרב *Amar Rav Chananya
ben Shemaya mishmei deRav*
it was said in the name of רב *Rav* כנגדו ביום טוב
ומותר *kenegdo beYom Tov umutar*
you can do the same thing on יום טוב *Yom Tov* because
even though there using your hand is a definite מלאכה *melacha* nevertheless
we're talking that it was being done without intention and therefore it's
מותר *mutar*. And now the גמרא *Gemara* gets into an interesting discussion
about doing things without intention. Ironic yes go ahead I just have
a few minutes I want to read a few more lines. Yes
okay.
Isn't it expected that it's going to happen?
Ah
so that's what the גמרא *Gemara* is going to say. Expected maybe,
definite no. And definite but we're going to talk about that right
now. So let's read the next line. So מי אמר רב הכי
*mi amar Rav hachi* did רב *Rav* really say that דבר שאינו
מתכוין *davar she'eino miskavein* is מותר *mutar*? והאמר רב *veha'amar Rav* רב
חייא בר אשי משמיה דרב *Rav Chiya bar Ashi mishmei deRav* רב
חייא בר אשי *Rav Chiya bar Ashi* said in the name of
רב *Rav* מסוכרייא
דנזייתא *masuchraya denazaita*. So anybody who's learned שבת *Shabbos* knows the famous
case of מסוכרייא דנזייתא *masuchraya denazaita*. If you look at תוספות *Tosafot*
תוספות *Tosafot* says here one sentence פירשנו בפרק קמא דכתובות ובסוף שמונה
עשר *perashnu beperek kama deKesuvos uvesof shmoneh asar* whatever meaning because there's
huge תוספותים *Tosafotim* over there so here he's not going to bother
to go into it. This is a classic case about שבת *Shabbos*
of דבר שאינו מתכוין *davar she'eino miskavein*. It is that you have
as your stopper for your wine barrel you have a rag. So
you got a hole in your wine barrel you put a rag
you tighted it into the hole that's your stopper. What's the problem
though? What happens to that rag when it's in the wine bottle?
It absorbs wine. What happens the next time you stop it up
and you put it squeeze it into that hole? The wine squeezes
out. So are you allowed to use it on שבת *Shabbos* and
יום טוב *Yom Tov* if you are going to inadvertently but almost
definitely squeeze out wine? And רב *Rav* says you can't. So look
אינו מתכוין *eino miskavein* and he says it's אסור *assur*. How here
does he say אינו מתכוין *eino miskavein* is מותר *mutar*? So the
גמרא *Gemara* says והאמר רב משמיה *veha'amar Rav mishmei* מסוכרייא דנזייתא אסור
להדוקא ביומא טבא *masuchraya denazaita assur lehadeka beyoma tava*. You cannot tighten
it on יום טוב *Yom Tov* because it'll inadvertently squeeze out the
wine. So the גמרא *Gemara* says נהי דאפילו רבי שמעון מודה *nehi
de'afilu Rabbi Shimon modeh* even רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* who is the
proponent of the position that דבר שאינו מתכוין *davar she'eino miskavein* is
מותר *mutar* even he would not go that far. Even he would
say that you can't do that. Why not? Because of what David
said that אביי ורבא דאמרי תרווייהו *Abaye veRava de'amri tarveihu* אביי *Abaye*
and רבא *Rava* both say מודה רבי שמעון בפסיק רישא ולא ימות
*modeh Rabbi
Shimon bepsik reisha velo yamut*. רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* agrees that if
you chop off something's head if you chop off its head will
it not die? Which basically means that if there is a definite
consequence even if unintended you can't chop off a chicken's head and
say I wasn't I wasn't intending for it to die. Okay so
if there's a definite consequence which is called in הלכה *halacha* פסיק
רישא *psik reisha* its head chopped off definite consequence you can the
fact that you say I didn't intend doesn't matter that it was
definitely going to come it's as if you did intend and it's
not a way of getting off. So therefore the גמרא *Gemara* says
yes רב *Rav* does say there's some cases of פסיק רישא *psik
reisha* where אינו מתכוין *eino miskavein* is a problem. But in our
משנה *Mishnah* again we will read our משנה *Mishnah* to say not
that you intentionally pulled hair you're just pushing it aside and it
happens unintentionally and as the גמרא *Gemara* now has to qualify it
like David said and it's not definitely going to get pulled out
because if it definitely would get pulled out that would be פסיק
רישא *psik reisha* and there we would agree.
And we also distinguish things that
are
definitely going to happen but are kind of side effects?
You mean מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה *melacha she'eina tzricha legufa*? Okay we'll
talk about that a little bit we'll talk about that tomorrow. Let
me read one more line about this and we'll wrap this up
for today. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like this ואמר רבי חייא
בר אשי אמר רב הלכה כרבי יהודה *ve'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi
amar Rav halacha keRabbi Yehuda*. Wait a minute fine if it were
רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* you could distinguish between the case of the
wine barrel which is definite and the case of the hair which
is you're framing it now as unintended and not definite. But רב
*Rav* himself rules like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. And רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* says דבר שאינו מתכוין *davar she'eino miskavein* is אסור *assur*. If
something now what does it mean דבר שאינו מתכוין *davar she'eino miskavein*
is אסור *assur*? How can you tell me not to do something
if I wasn't intending to do it? It means don't do something
that might lead to a certain result even if you don't care
even if you're not intending that. So don't go ahead and pull
a the classic example is pull a bench through a garden because
it might create a furrow even though you're not caring or
intending. Don't go ahead and pull wool aside from a sheep because
hair might get pulled out. Okay that should be what רב *Rav*
should say if he rules like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda*. So how could רב *Rav* explain the משנה *Mishnah* based
on אינו מתכוין *eino miskavein*? And let's see and let's just go
through the list רב חננאל בר אמי אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי שמעון
*Rav Chananel bar Ami amar Shmuel halacha keRabbi Shimon*. So there's so
שמואל *Shmuel* holds like רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. ורב חייא בר אבין
מתני בלא גברי *veRav Chiya bar Avin masni bela gavrei* and רב
חייא בר אבין *Rav Chiya bar Avin* just says straight without the
whole tradition of who said in the name of רב *Rav* in
the name of שמואל *Shmuel* just straight רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel*.
רב אמר הלכה כרבי יהודה שמואל אמר הלכה כרבי שמעון *Rav amar
halacha keRabbi Yehuda Shmuel amar halacha keRabbi Shimon*. So it's a debate
of רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel*. But רב *Rav* says אינו מתכוין
*eino miskavein* is forbidden. So how does how can he say that
the משנה *Mishnah* we rule like our משנה *Mishnah* and it's based
on אינו מתכוין *eino miskavein*? אלא *Ela* the גמרא *Gemara* says you're
right לעולם סבר רב דבר שאינו מתכוין אסור *le'olam savar Rav davar
she'eino miskavein assur*. He says unintended is forbidden and that's not the
reason of the משנה *Mishnah*. So then what is the reason? reason
of the משנה *mishna*, right? And we don't want to say that
תולש *tolesh* isn't גוזז *gozez* because we're applying the משנה *mishna* to
יום טוב *Yom Tov*. Okay? So the other approach would have been
to say, yeah, using your hand is fundamentally not the same act.
But then we wouldn't be able to apply it to יום טוב
*Yom Tov*. So you can't say אינו מתכוין *eino miskaven*, you've chosen
to say not to be able to say that it's not the
act of תולש *tolesh*. What's פשט *pshat* in the משנה *mishna*? So
the גמרא *Gemara* says, ותולש לאו היינו
גוזז *ve'tolesh lav hainu gozez*. Yes, we will continue to assert that
תולש *tolesh* is not גוזז *gozez* and that's the meaning of the
משנה *mishna* and therefore you can do it intentionally. Thank God, because
that's a much better read of the משנה *mishna*. But then how
can you apply it to יום טוב *Yom Tov*? If יום טוב
*Yom Tov* תולש *tolesh* is certainly a מלאכה *melacha*. וביום טוב היינו
טעמא דשרי *u've'Yom Tov hainu ta'ama de'shari*. Here's why it's permitted. דהוה
ליה עוקר דבר מגידולו *de'hava lei oker davar mi'gidulo*. Yes, it's a
מלאכה *melacha*. You're being abstracted as uprooting something from where it grows,
but whatever, it's definitely a מלאכה *melacha*. But כלאחר יד *ke'le'achar yad*,
but you're doing it in an unusual way. So that is very
important with the distinguishing between what does it mean to do something
differently. Sometimes when you do it differently, you're doing a completely different
act, right? If I go and I get a haircut as opposed
to I'm pulling out my hair, it's not like pulling out my
hair is getting a haircut in a strange way. It's fundamentally a
different act. That's what the גמרא *Gemara* says, תולש לאו היינו גוזז
*tolesh lav hainu gozez*. Okay. Now, on the other hand, if I
go ahead and I get a haircut and I use, you know,
my
weak hand or something, or I do it, I have developed a
skill that I can do it with my, you know, I can
use my toes to give somebody a haircut, you know, with the
scissors, that's כלאחר יד *ke'le'achar yad*, but it's still a haircut, just
done in a bizarre way. So sometimes when does the change make
it a different act and when does it make it the same
act done in a strange way? So the גמרא *Gemara* says like
this: pulling out hair as opposed to cutting it is a different
act. It's תולש *tolesh*. And therefore for בכור *bechor*, we have no
concept of an abstract category, we just have גוזז *gozez*, and therefore
it's a completely different act and you could do it even intentionally.
And that's פשט *pshat* in our משנה *mishna*. Now you move to
יום טוב *Yom Tov*. יום טוב *Yom Tov* it doesn't have to
be תולש *tolesh*. It doesn't have to be גוזז *gozez*. It's a
bigger and more abstract category. And even if it was a pulling
out, that would be considered to be, it affected the same end
result. It got the hair removed and that should be enough for
יום טוב *Yom Tov*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says you're right, it
did get the same end result removed, but anybody who wants hair
doesn't do it by pulling using their hand. So the using of
the hand is not because it's defined as תולש *tolesh* versus גוזז
*gozez*. We don't care what the technical narrow definition is. But what
we do care about is any normal person that wants this end
result does not do it through the act of pulling it out.
So since you do it in a strange way, therefore you're exempt
for יום טוב *Yom Tov*. Now the question is normally we say
that when you do it in a strange way you're exempt, you're
exempt, we don't say that it's allowed. Why here is it going
to be straight away allowed? So the answer would be we're allowing
it for the sake of שחיטה *shechita*. Since we allow שחיטה *shechita*
for יום טוב *Yom Tov* and that's in order to have food
and whatever, there are some types of things that we do allow
that we normally wouldn't, but at the rabbinic level in order to
make it possible for you to have שחיטה *shechita*. Okay, so that's
the simple way to read the סוגיא *sugya*. תוספות *Tosafot* raises the
question James did, which was about מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה *melacha she'eina
tzricha le'gufa*. You're not interested in the hair, right? For שבת *Shabbos*
and יום טוב *Yom Tov* the question is also whether you care
about, whether you're interested in the end result. Not what you intended,
but are you interested? So תוספות *Tosafot* says, yeah, that's also a
factor we could have introduced because you don't want the hair. Right.
Exactly. So anyway, okay, if we were learning more שבת *Shabbos* and
יום טוב *Yom Tov*, maybe we'll talk about it more tomorrow. But
anyway, just mention that תוספות *Tosafot* also tries to suggest that in
all the cases of the גמרא *Gemara* it's never thinking that you
could do it intentionally. Even when it's saying it's not גוזז *gozez*,
it's כלאחר יד *ke'le'achar yad*, that also, that still it's still committed
to the idea that you're doing it unintended. But that is not
the simple פשט *pshat* of the גמרא *Gemara*. So the simple פשט
*pshat* of the גמרא *Gemara* here is that you can read the
משנה *mishna* intentional. It's not the same act when you use your
hand. When you use your hand it's not the same act, it's
not גוזז *gozez*. When it comes to יום טוב *Yom Tov* you
don't need the same act, but you do need it to be
done in a normal way. And using your hand isn't normal and
therefore it's allowed for יום טוב *Yom Tov* even though normally that
would be a rabbinic problem, here we allow it for שחיטה *shechita*.